Hey everyone, it's your friendly
neighborhood watching the Plain Bagel.
Today, I wanted to give an update on a
topic that I covered just under 2 years
ago of sketchy companies paying
YouTubers to promote their publicly
traded stocks. If you never saw the
original video, the gist is that we saw
this trend of influencers promoting
really
questionable investment opportunities.
And I'm not talking about NFTs or
cryptocurrencies, but rather publicly
traded stocks where the companies were
often earning zero dollars of revenue or
spending more on investor relations like
these promotions than actually
developing their business with even a
few of them being on the verge of
bankruptcy, admitting in their filings
that there was serious doubt about their
ability to continue as a going concern.
And yet these companies were often being
advertised as a huge investment
opportunity, a company that was about to
take advantage of some meaningful macro
trend and experience a massive
turnaround. Even though most of the
stocks, as of the time of the video, had
actually fallen in value from when they
were promoted. Now, when I first posted
on this topic, a number of creators
eventually deleted their videos. Uh one
creator even actually responded with a
video of their own. And admittedly, I
was hopeful that maybe this was just a a
short-lived fad, a temporary fluke. And
like the annoying trends of influencers
promoting NFTs and meme
cryptocurrencies, that this would seem
be a thing of the past.
Uh but, you know, the reason I'm
covering it today is no, that's that's
not what we've seen
in the slightest. There continue to be a
slew of influencers promoting these
companies to their viewers across
Instagram, TikTok, X, and seemingly
largest of all, YouTube. Some of the
channels are specifically in the finance
niche. A number are political or
geopolitical commentators. And I've even
come across some massive science
channels with millions of subscribers
promoting these investments despite the
fact again, these companies aren't
making any money. They they don't have
any sales. But beyond this trend just
continuing, it's also been evolving. Now
companies are promoting their sketchy
stocks using AI influencers,
artificially generated videos that can't
even pronounce their disclosures
properly. Disseminated on behalf of
Stream X Corp. What have things come to?
Soon you won't even be able to lose your
money to real finfluencers anymore. What
kind of country are we if we let this
happen? Even Kristi Noem, the former US
Secretary of Homeland Security, has
herself gotten involved with one of
these sketchy zero revenue companies
that's advertising heavily on YouTube
using these AI ads. And of course, it's
all topped off with the recent news from
the Wall Street Journal on Polymarket,
the prediction market that was recently
found to be paying creators in the US to
promote its offerings without disclosing
payment for the promotions. So you can
see that this type of questionable
influencer marketing is really reaching
a bit of a boiling point. And it's
really concerning for a number of
reasons. One, uh the rules around
promoting financial services, platforms,
and products through influencers remains
a pretty ambiguous area. Uh two,
finfluencers are only becoming more and
more prevalent and more relied on for
financial information. One Finra survey
found that 61% of people aged 18 to 34
have made investment decisions based on
recommendations from a social media
personality versus roughly a quarter
across age groups. And three, as we're
seeing, even when people break the
rules, there doesn't seem to be much
fear of retribution. One investigation
by the CFA Research and Policy Center
from 2024
found that only half of finfluencer
promotions on social media contained
proper disclosure. And yet we still
haven't seen a meaningful crackdown on
that activity. And in fact, quite the
opposite, we've seen a real regulatory
pullback in the US. And even here in
Canada, where we've had examples of
finfluencers being fined, the
punishments just really haven't been
enough to discourage this activity. And
so I wanted to give an update on things
to talk about the current state of this
type of promotional activity, the
continuing examples we've seen, uh some
of the changes we're seeing from
regulators, and the expected changes
because there is sort of this
expectation of a crackdown to come.
There was also actually a research paper
that was published that actually
referenced my initial video, which
obviously pretty cool to see, so I
wanted to touch on that. And just
generally, I wanted to raise awareness
on this issue once again and highlight
what people can do if they come across
these sketchy advertisements because
I've had the opportunity to speak with
regulators on this exact issue. And so I
wanted to share some resources and uh
what can be done to
I guess better put this issue on the
radar of lawmakers and the like. But I
want to start off with a quick overview
of that Wall Street Journal
investigation into Polymarket because it
really helps to set the scene for
everything else. Uh and it's also what's
gone the topic into the news cycle
currently. The gist of the article is
that even though Polymarket is banned
from operating its main platform in the
United States, the company has hired a
marketing agency that's paying mostly
college-aged creators to promote the
platform with so-called clippers
recirculating content to rake up views.
With the report finding that creators
were actually instructed at times not to
disclose that they were being paid. With
this just being one of the major
revelations from this article, the
investigation also found that the
creators were often placing fake bets in
their videos using a dummy website set
up by Polymarket called Poy Market where
the I was capitalized to look like the
normal URL. And despite creators
claiming to have made money from their
bets totaling almost $900,000,
the journalists found that the bets
would have actually lost a total of
$166,000.
Now, we've covered prediction markets
before and highlighted the fact that
most people lose money, uh
like you would expect from a typical
gambling platform. But, most of these
ads really talked up the money-making
opportunities of the platform. There's
this excellent infographic from the
article that highlights the common
phrases from these promotions. And you
can see that 25% of the ads included the
term free, often alluding to the idea
that a given bet was free money. Now,
beyond the whole not disclosing the
promotion thing, uh which regardless of
whether something's a financial service
or not is not generally allowed by the
FTC in the US, uh you can see that these
promotions really fly in the face of the
typical requirements for promoting
financial products and services. Uh
there are a lot of restrictions around
messaging when you talk about mutual
funds or typically publicly traded
stocks with traditional avenues. Uh you
can't suggest future performance, return
figures have to be standardized, and if
you're a registered investment advisor
advertising an investment, there are a
lot of general restrictions in terms of
how you can format your advertisement.
But, in this case, Polymarket is
somewhat pleading ignorance because they
hired a marketing agency and are
claiming that they themselves weren't
privy to how these promotions were being
carried out. Uh but, a separate
investigation, funny enough, by Politico
found that there were at least 490
instances of a Polymarket paid creator
promoting the platform on X without
clearly disclosing the partnership. With
payments for these arrangements coming
from the personal PayPal account of
Matthew Mottahedeh, the company's chief
marketing officer. So, yeah, some pretty
damning revelations. Now, I won't dive
deeper into that story. If you want
more, you can check out this video from
Coffeezilla where he talks to the two
journalists behind these articles. Uh
sorry, Voidzilla, not Coffeezilla. I
always mix up those two creators. Uh
but, you can see it paints a pretty
depressing picture about the state of
financial advertising, at least in the
United States. But, maybe that's to be
expected. We are talking about
prediction markets here after all, which
have been sketchy from the beginning and
just generally legally contested and
precarious. So, it'd be a nice thought
to think this is the only place where
that kind of stuff is happening, but
sadly, no. Uh the reason I'm here is
because that's not the case. We continue
to see really sketchy stock promotion
campaigns on YouTube and other platforms
where multiple creators are paid to
promote companies with really
questionable financials. Now, unlike
with the Polymarket story, I would say
the majority of the videos I've come
across anyway do disclose their
partnership in some manner. In fact,
that's really the only way I can come
across these examples is by searching
for these key terms that come up with
these disclosures. And some of these
companies may very well just be trying
to raise capital from investors for a
business opportunity, and that retail
market is really the only group they
have access to. This video by Economics
Explained, for example, promotes
Enhanced Group, ticker ENHA, the company
behind the Enhanced Games, which for the
uninitiated is like the Olympics but on
steroids.
Literally. Which, don't get me wrong, is
still a choice to promote. It's also
problematic given that the promotion
isn't disclosed in the video itself.
There's just this tag and then a
disclosure deep in the description box.
But, at least in this example, there's
some justification for why we don't have
any historical revenue. But, beyond the
concerns of trying to pump a stock's
price, with there being examples of
companies paying creators to promote
their stock and then shortly after
issuing or selling shares, a lot of
these companies just don't appear to be
making any real progress towards making
any money. A lot are mineral and mining
companies that own some sort of land or
asset, but they aren't really developing
it. They're just selling the dream that
they might one day, or that they'll
eventually be bought for their land by a
bigger developer. Which might sound
promising when these videos bring up
macro trends and surging prices for
commodities and metals, until you see
that most of these companies have
already been around for over a decade
and have survived off investor funds the
whole while. There's also something
called a lifestyle company, which is a
business that basically exists to funnel
investor money to its executive team.
It's investors paying for the lifestyle
of business management who are taking
salaries and bonuses all the while not
making any progress on the actual
company. And while some creators do
highlight that these are high-risk
investments,
>> This is a speculative junior mining
stock.
>> In other cases, the discrepancy between
what's being sold and the reality of the
investment
is a canyon. It's pretty stark. Take
this video by The Invisible Hand for
example, a geopolitics channel that
frequently gets hundreds of thousands of
views. It includes a promotion for Giant
Mining Corp, ticker symbol BFFGF,
where by the creator talks about these
macro trends of the US trying to onshore
copper production and how that sets the
company up nicely to take advantage
given that they own some copper plays.
There's a lot of talk of upside with
this advertisement, but very little
mention of risk. With really the only
thing being the video highlighting that
the company owns a past producing mine
in Nevada. In other words, they don't
currently have active operations. They
own a mine that used to make copper but
doesn't anymore. But based on this ad,
that hardly seems like an issue.
>> The infrastructure is [music] ready.
Access roads, power supply,
transportation, water supply, ore
stockpiles,
>> [music]
>> and established road access.
>> But here's the thing. If you look into
the company's filings, beyond the fact
that they haven't earned any revenue
since their founding in 2017,
you'll see that they also don't have any
known mineral reserves, mineral
resources, or body of commercially
viable ore. In other words, while they
might have some copper in the mine they
own, it's not feasible that it can be
extracted. If if to click the link for
the promotion, you'll see that it
actually directs you to a page for
CopperOne Resource. Because even though
this video is from this year, the
company recently underwent a name
change. It's fifth such name change
since it was originally founded 9 years
ago. Also, if you look up here on their
Cedar profile, which is the regulatory
website we're currently on, you can see
that they actually have some
disciplinary action flags for making
false or misleading statements and
misrepresentations. With past violations
even leading to trading bans on certain
insiders. Needless to say, a few red
flags here that most people should
probably vet before they, you know,
choose to promote this company to
millions of viewers. And yet, these are
the businesses that a slew of creators
have chosen to partner with. Uh some of
whom put themselves out there as
financial experts, people who know how
to analyze a stock. And yet, are
seemingly missing all these details or
potentially worse, ignoring or choosing
to actively omit this information. It
also brings me to the update around
Kristi Noem, which I find hilarious. I
was scrolling the news one day and I saw
this update that former US Homeland
Security Secretary Kristi Noem had been
hired by British Columbia mining company
Novared Mining to help the company with
its mission of, quote, "acquiring and
advancing critical mineral exploration
opportunities through its artificial
intelligence enhanced technology
platform." Now, right away, like a hawk
spotting a mouse in a cornfield, this
caught my eye. Uh given A, British
Columbia mining company tends to be the
background of many of these zero revenue
companies, and B, the AI buzzword being
mentioned in their mission statement
randomly. But to my surprise, they
weren't paying finfluencers to promote
their company.
But rather something much worse.
Instead, they've just had channels
posting a bunch of AI slop to promote
their publicly traded stock.
>> Brian is the CEO of Enred with over 15
years in mineral exploration and gold
and copper discovery projects.
>> Which, hey, to their credit, I guess is
the AI technology they were talking
about. And this is something that I've
started to see more examples of.
Companies using AI generated influencers
or videos to promote their stock. And I
find that all this both hilarious and
depressing. On the one hand, we're
seeing companies cut out the middleman
of the finfluencer to direct market
their their crappy stock promotions
directly to investors. But on the other
hand, these types of videos are getting
harder and harder to detect. And with
people like Kristi Noem being brought
into the mix, it feels like these
companies are really trying to onboard
some people with pretty large followings
or at least a public presence to amplify
their messaging beyond the sort of
finfluencer ecosystem. And the worst
part about all of this
is that the promotions
seemingly work. If you watch my original
video, you know that I put together a
list of over 100 pieces of content that
included these types of paid promotions.
Well, funny enough, some researchers
from Brazil actually used the
spreadsheet that I put out for a
research paper titled Pay to Pump that
was published in Applied Economics
Letters. Whereby they found that
promoted stocks on YouTube saw an
average return of 7.9%
on release date, but that they reverted
back to pre-promotion levels within 30
days. And it might lead you to wonder,
Richard,
how is any of this allowed? Well, even
if a sponsorship is properly disclosed,
there's a chance that some of these ads
aren't. Many of these publicly traded
stocks are actually based in Canada,
namely British Columbia. And British
Columbia securities law requires that
advertising issuers provide balanced
messaging when advertising their stock.
In fact, we've seen Canadian regulators
raise concerns in the past over
advertisements on TV that don't disclose
enough information about the risks of a
position. And in my own non-legal expert
opinion, I want to be very clear on
that. Um
seems like we're kind of seeing that
here. However, one issue is that
Canada's securities laws are
predominantly principles-based. So,
there's not a long, comprehensive list
of rules, which leaves a lot of gray
area and stuff that's basically up for
interpretation until the issue is ruled
on. Now, regulators have made some
efforts to try and clear things up. In
December, they actually released some
guidance for finfluencers about staying
within the law, highlighting, for
example, that finfluencer promotion
disclosure must be, quote, clear and
inconspicuous. With the document
including a number of examples of what
would cross the line, with one being,
for example, that regulators would not
consider a disclosure sufficient if it's
placed at the end of a long video, or if
the reader needs to make additional
clicks to hear or see the information in
full, or if it's just generally
confusing or unclear. But, that still
leaves a lot up for interpretation. How
long is a long video? What exactly needs
to be included in this disclosure? Does
the includes paid promotion tag on
YouTube suffice?
Now, in speaking with regulators, I can
tell you that it doesn't, but you get my
point, right? There's a lot up for
interpretation, which can make it
difficult to crack down on this
activity, especially when jurisdiction
comes up as an issue.
Like I mentioned, most of these
companies are based in Canada, but a
good chunk of the creators are based in
the US or even, at times, other
international markets, which brings up
the question of whose rules does this
fall under? Now, there are also rules in
the US about how to advertise investment
opportunities, but it's unclear about
when they apply to finfluencers,
especially because, as we've covered in
previous videos, finfluencers are
generally exempt from registration
requirements. And while regulators are
trying to make it clear that that
doesn't exempt them from liability with
these promotions, it does seem like many
of these companies are trying to take
advantage of the fact that these
finfluencers don't have as many rules
applied to them. So, you can see that
we're in a pretty sad state of affairs,
and one reason for that is seemingly
that there isn't much fear of
retribution at the moment. In the
Coffeezilla video where he again
interviewed the journalists behind the
two Polymarket investigations, it's
highlighted that while they shared their
findings with the FTC, they didn't
really get any sort of response that
would suggest that they would act on it.
It's hard not to feel hopeless when you
see stories of the president of the
United States making hundreds of
millions of dollars on the launch of his
own meme coin that most investors lost
money on. His family having these of
interests with prediction markets, and
the CFTC seemingly suing on behalf of
prediction markets to keep them out of
stricter gambling laws. And even here in
Canada, like I mentioned with the stock
promotions, we just haven't seen much of
a crackdown. Last year, the big story in
the space was that a creator by the name
of
had been fined by the Alberta Securities
Commission for skirting disclosure
requirements. He had posted a bunch of
videos without making it clear that they
were paid promotions for the stocks he
was talking about. In some cases,
forgoing a disclosure altogether or just
hiding it under the show more button of
the YouTube description box. Because the
creator had found them when he disclosed
the payments, he got fewer views.
Shocker. Now, the creator was penalized.
He was barred from similar activity for
2 years and is paying around $40,000 in
fines. But if you look at the ruling,
you can see that the creator actually
made over $100,000
from his posts. With the creator being
able to argue legally that he shouldn't
be subject to disgorgement. So, it's no
wonder why these issues are only getting
worse. These companies are throwing so
much money at creators well above the
typical going rates for sponsorships,
and many are willing to take the brand
hit and legal risk to make that money,
especially when the few times there is a
punishment, it really just looks like a
slap on the wrist or the cost of doing
business. And look, I know, people
shouldn't just follow the investment
advice of creators online. We all know
about the conflicts of interest.
But people aren't rational with money.
We've long known that people are
susceptible to this type of marketing
when they're in a dire financial
situation or don't have that financial
background. These people are presenting
a cure to a lot of these people's
problems and that can be compelling when
you're not in a position to objectively
analyze the message. And when you can't
even tell if the content you're watching
is a paid advertisement, that's a huge
issue and one that's going to have a
financial impact on viewers. This isn't
an overpriced merchandise sweater. This
is finances. This is something that's
going to impact potentially someone's
life savings. Now,
taking a breath.
It all brings me to why I wanted to make
this video. Over the past 6 months, I've
actually been traveling a bit to speak
on these issues with securities
regulators. I spoke at both the North
American Securities Administrators
Association and Canadian Investment
Regulatory Organization conferences. And
in addition to being able to raise some
of these issues, I've also been able to
have a number of conversations directly
with enforcement officers and other
members of these regulatory
organizations. And it did help to convey
a few things. For one, enforcement
agents are aware of many of these issues
and do carry out some actions behind the
scenes that we don't see publicly,
things like cease and desists, uh
requiring disclosure updates, and even
taking down channels or websites when
there's explicit legal activity. Two,
regulators are increasingly looking to
better monitor finfluencer activity and
maybe cracking down on the space. Uh
we've had a number of initiatives uh in
Canada at least to engage with
finfluencers via information sessions to
better communicate again where those red
lines are. Uh there's likely to be more
guidance to come out in terms of uh the
rules that finfluencers need to follow.
The idea has even been floated to follow
the Australia model whereby finfluencers
would require a form of registration so
that they would be better monitored and
have strict rules to follow. And
starting last year, the UK Financial
Conduct Authority actually started an
annual global week of action against
unlawful finfluencers, where 17
regulatory bodies, including regulators
in Canada, coordinated a crackdown on
unlawful activity. Now, the US wasn't a
part of that, but we did see a number of
influencers charged and fined as a
result of those efforts. With the BCSC
actually bringing another case against
outlets VHLA and Black Swan for similar
improper disclosure of promotional
content. And three, the best way to help
these regulators and get the issue
better on the radar of lawmakers is to
report these videos and unlawful
promotions when they occur. There are a
number of reporting and whistleblower
programs across the Canadian and US
regulators that you can report videos to
if you believe they are crossing line
around improper disclosure or how
they're representing an investment.
Jurisdiction is a tricky thing, but you
can report based on where the company
that's being promoted is based or where
the finfluencer themselves is based. And
some of these programs actually offer a
cash reward if the investigation results
in a fine. Alternatively, I've set up a
new email that I'll show on screen to
avoid bots as best I can that you can
send pieces of content you come across
that you believe is crossing a line
because it'll help to better inform my
own content and also better inform any
future conversation I might be able to
have with regulators as I've been very
privileged in my ability to speak
directly with a number of these bodies.
So, that's my call to action for this
video. I know things are rough, but
hopefully if nothing else, this at least
helps to discourage some of the most
blatant stuff we come across. Thanks for
watching. Let me know your thoughts down
below on what you think should be done
about finfluencers and these promotions
that we're seeing. I've been very honest
in a lot of these conversations with
regulators that I don't know what the
perfect solution is beyond just more
explicit enforcement of the rules that
do exist. But I'd be curious to hear
your thoughts down below in terms of
what changes you think should be made.
Thanks again for joining me and as
always
be safe out there.